Guide to the George Ellery Hale Papers HaleGE
California Institute of Technology Archives and Special Collections
George Ellery Hale Papers
1863-1950
1882-1938
California Institute of Technology Archives and Special Collections
Hale, George Ellery, 1868-1938
HaleGE
73 linear feet 175 boxes
Digitized: this collection is available on the web. George Ellery Hale (1868–1938) was an influential astrophysicist and science administrator. This collection of Hale's scientific, professional, and personal papers documents his roles in inventing the spectrohelioscope; promoting international cooperation among scientists; and founding major observatories, as well as the California Institute of Technology, Huntington Library, Astrophysical Journal, and National Research Council.
Conditions Governing Access
Most of this collection is available on the web, linked from individual folder records in this finding aid. The original paper copies of the first nine series are located at the Caltech Archives, where access is available to anyone conducting research for which it is necessary; please contact the Caltech Archives to make an appointment. The original Director's Files of the Mount Wilson Observatory are located at the Huntington Library, where they are available to qualified researchers by application through their Reader Services Department.
Existence and Location of Copies
In 1968, the Carnegie Institution of Washington and the California Institute of Technology used funds from the National Historical Publications Commission to publish a microfilm edition of 100 rolls that includes most of the contents of the Hale Papers. In 2018, Caltech, the Huntington Library, and the Carnegie Institution collaborated to digitize this microfilm edition, creating a web edition which is linked from individual folder records in this finding aid. Both the microfilm edition and the web edition omit portions of the collection, which are noted throughout the finding aid.
Arrangement
The heart of the Hale collection consists of the personal and organizational correspondence and the Director's Files of the Mount Wilson Observatory. All three of these groups should be used together. Since Hale's own arrangement of his files was respected in the organization of the collection, the personal correspondence contains scattered files on organizations. Furthermore, all three groups of files contain material related to individuals, organizations, and problems in science. For example, a good deal of information on the Mount Wilson Observatory is in the Robert S. Woodward file, among many others, in the personal section. Similarly, substantial material on William W. Campbell is to be found in the National Academy of Sciences files in the organizational section. Cross-checking for material on given subjects must also be done within particular sections. For instance, the files on international scientific organizations, which deal mainly with the International Research Council and its associated Unions, may be used together with the records relating to the National Academy of Sciences and the National Research Council.
Biographical / Historical
George Ellery Hale was born in Chicago in 1868. After receiving his B.S. from MIT in 1890, he quickly established a scientific reputation for his invention of the spectroheliograph, then made important contributions to the study of solar phenomena, organized and coedited the Astrophysical Journal, and led the design, funding and construction of the Kenwood, Yerkes, Mount Wilson and Palomar Observatories. In 1904, Hale became director of the Mount Wilson Observatory and settled in Pasadena, California, where became deeply involved in local education and culture, including the creation of Caltech and the Huntington Library. Meanwhile, he revivified the National Academy of Sciences by organizing the National Research Council, obtaining a substantial endowment, and establishing the National Research Council Fellowships. Before World War I, Hale was a founder of the International Union of Cooperation in Solar Research, Foreign Secretary of the National Academy of Sciences, and frequent delegate to the International Association of Academies. After the war, he was instrumental in the establishment of the International Research Council and served as president of its successor, the International Council of Scientific Unions, from 1931 to 1934. Hale died in 1938.
Custodial History
At the time of Hale's death his papers were located at the headquarters of the Mount Wilson Obervatory. Within a few years his secretary, Louise F. Gianetti, separated the papers that she judged to be part of his personal collection from those that pertained to the affairs of the Observatory. These personal papers, filling some 28 file drawers, were moved to the attic of Hale's own solar laboratory on Holladay Road in Pasadena. The Observatory papers, occupying some 9 file drawers, remained at the Mount Wilson headquarters.
Hale's personal papers were placed in the custody of the California Institute of Technology by his heirs in 1966. At that time, a new administrative building for the Mount Wilson Observatory was planned, and the Hale papers were to be brought together into one unified collection and housed within that structure. This building was never built. Further, the agreement between the California Institute of Technology and the Carnegie Institution of Washington for the joint operation of the Mount Wilson and Palomar Observatories, established in 1948, was dissolved in 1980. A few years later, the Carnegie Institution turned over its Hale manuscripts, the so-called Director's Files, to the Huntington Library, along with other materials relating to the Mount Wilson Observatory, including a rare book collection. The remainder of the Hale papers—by far the bulk of the manuscript material—remained in the custody of Caltech. According to Evelina Hale's original stipulation, they were to do so until the completion of the new building which would house the collection—a project which was ultimately never completed. Thus the Hale papers are divided between two neighboring institutions, and each administers its portion.
Existence and Location of Originals
Series 1 through 9 are located at the Caltech Archives. The Director's Files of the Mount Wilson Observatory are located at the Huntington Library.
Related Materials
Other manuscript collections which contain material relevant to Hale's life include the records of the National Academy of Sciences National Research Council at the Academy's headquarters in Washington, D.C.; the John C. Merriam Papers at the Library of Congress; the Harry M. Goodwin Papers at the Huntington Library; and the Robert A. Millikan Papers and Helen Wright Collection at the California Institute of Technology.
Scope and Contents
This collection provides a thorough record of George Ellery Hale's activities. A prolific correspondent, Hale kept copies of most of his letters. The collections contains significant material relating to the theoretical and instrumental development of astrophysics, the history of the Mount Wilson and Palomar Observatories, and the early history of the California Institute of Technology. It also documents Hale's work with the National Academy of Sciences and National Research Council.
Astronomical observatories; Spectrohelioscope; Astrophysics; Astrophysicists
- Personal Correspondence and Papers Relating to Individuals, 1865–1950; 1; 20 linear feet (Tape HaleGE_01, Carton 1, Reel 1–40, Carton 3)
  - Cleveland Abbe, 1903; HaleGE_01_00_001_01; Hale, George Ellery, 1868-1938; 2 pages (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Existence and Location of Copies
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 1, frames 20 to 22.
    Astronomy; Mount Whitney (Calif.); Washington (D.C.); Williams Bay (Wis.); Hale, George Ellery, 1868-1938
  - C. G. Abbot, 1902–1937; HaleGE_01_00_001_02; Smithsonian Institution; Michelson, Albert A. (Albert Abraham), 1852-1931; Hale, George Ellery, 1868-1938; University of Chicago; 348 pages This file includes telegrams, schematics, postcards, and tables. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 1, frames 23 to 370.
    Solar radiation; Mount Whitney (Calif.); Astronomy; Astrophysics; Meteorology; Pasadena (Calif.); Williams Bay (Wis.); Washington (D.C.); Medals and awards; Hooker telescope; Sunspots; Astronomical observatories; Astronomy--Research; Millikan, Robert Andrews, 1868-1953 (Experimental Physicist, Nobel Laureate, Caltech President); Noyes, Arthur A. (Arthur Amos), 1866-1936; Hale, George Ellery, 1868-1938; Babcock, Horace W.; Brockett, Paul, 1872-1946; Merriam, John C., 1869-1945; Curie, Marie, 1867-1934; Carnegie Institution of Washington; National Research Council (U.S.); Lorentz, H. A. (Hendrik Antoon), 1853-1928; California Institute of Technology
  - John Jacob Abel, 1915–1936; HaleGE_01_00_001_03; Hale, George Ellery, 1868-1938; 67 pages This file contains postcards. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 1, frames 371 to 438.
    Chemistry; Physics; Pharmacology; Physiology -- History; Astronomy; Pasadena (Calif.); Chicago, IL; Baltimore, MD; Hooker telescope; Awards; Nobel Prize; Nobel Prize winners; Stockholm (Sweden); Hale, George Ellery, 1868-1938; Michelson, Albert A. (Albert Abraham), 1852-1931; Einstein, Albert, 1879-1955; Curie, Marie, 1867-1934; Rutherford (Ernest), 1871-1937; National Research Council (U.S.); Planck, Max, 1858-1947
  - Giorgio Abetti, 1909–1935; HaleGE_01_00_001_04; Hale, George Ellery, 1868-1938; Pease, Francis; Carnegie Institution of Washington; 698 pages his file contains newspaper articles, telegrams, schematics, segments from a manual, postcards, photos, spectrographs, and heliograph slabs. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 1, frames 439 to 1137.
    Astronomy; Astronomical observatories; Physics; Engineering; Chemistry; Solar radiation; World War I; Telescopes--Design; Earthquakes; Mount Wilson Observatory; Astrophysics; Geology; Navy -- United States; Science--Political aspects; World War, 1914-1918--Science--United States; Medals and awards; Washington (D.C.); Pasadena, CA; Paris (France); Rome; Arcetri (Italy); Florence (Italy); Millikan, Robert Andrews, 1868-1953 (Experimental Physicist, Nobel Laureate, Caltech President); Babcock, Harold D. (Harold Delos), 1882-1968; Michelson, Albert A. (Albert Abraham), 1852-1931; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924; Adams, Walter S. (Walter Sydney), 1876-1956; Hubble, Edwin; Campbell, W. W. (William Wallace); Carnegie Institution of Washington; National Research Council (U.S.); California Institute of Technology; Marconi, Guglielmo (Physicist, Nobel Laureate)
  - J. H. Abraham, 1902–1904; HaleGE_01_00_001_05; Hale, George Ellery, 1868-1938; 5 pages (Box 1, Folder 5)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 1, frames 1138 to 1143.
    Astronomy; Physics; Pasadena (Calif.); Paris (France); University of Chicago
  - Comfort A. Adams, 1919–1920; HaleGE_01_00_001_06; Hale, George Ellery, 1868-1938; 14 pages (Box 1, Folder 6)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 1, frames 1144 to 1158.
    Engineering; Geology; Geography; Applied physics; Chemistry; Pasadena (Calif.); Washington (D.C.); New York (N.Y.); National Research Council (U.S.); Hale, George Ellery, 1868-1938
  - Edward Dean Adams, 1920–1928; HaleGE_01_00_001_07; Hale, George Ellery, 1868-1938; Dunn, Gano, 1870-1953; 37 pages (Box 1, Folder 7)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 1, frames 1159 to 1196.
    Engineering; Astronomy; Medals and awards; Pasadena (Calif.); New York (N.Y.); Florence (Italy); Millikan, Robert Andrews, 1868-1953 (Experimental Physicist, Nobel Laureate, Caltech President); Edison, Thomas A. (Thomas Alva), 1847-1931; Hale, George Ellery, 1868-1938; National Research Council (U.S.); Hale, George Ellery, 1868-1938; Mount Wilson Observatory
  - Edward F. Adams, 1938; HaleGE_01_00_001_08; 1 pages (Box 1, Folder 8)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 1, frames 1197 to 1199.
    Pasadena (Calif.); Chicago, IL; Astronomy; Hale, George Ellery, 1868-1938
  - Walter S. Adams, 1904–1937; HaleGE_01_00_002_01; Adams, Walter S. (Walter Sydney), 1876-1956; Hale, George Ellery, 1868-1938; Woodward, Robert Simpson, 1849-1924; King, Arthur S. (Arthur Scott), 1879-1957; Carnegie Institution of Washington; National Research Council (U.S.); 630 pages (Box 2, Folder 1)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 2, frames 20 to 645.
    Astronomy; astronomers; Hooker telescope; Engineering; Meteorology; Telescopes--Design; Earthquakes; Sunspots; World War, 1914-1918--Science--United States; World War I; Fraunhofer lines; Stark effect; Mount Wilson Observatory; Noyes, Arthur A. (Arthur Amos), 1866-1936; Millikan, Robert Andrews, 1868-1953 (Experimental Physicist, Nobel Laureate, Caltech President); Michelson, Albert A. (Albert Abraham), 1852-1931; King, Arthur S. (Arthur Scott), 1879-1957; Merriam, John C., 1869-1945; Pease, Francis; Hubble, Edwin; Merrill, Paul Willard; Campbell, W. W. (William Wallace); Babcock, Harold D. (Harold Delos), 1882-1968; Ellerman, Ferdinand; Baker, Newton Diehl, 1871-1937; Conklin, Edwin Grant, 1863-1952; Anderson, John Augustus (Astronomer); Seares, Frederick H.; Maanen, Adriaan van; Nicholson, Seth; Humason, Milton; Smithsonian Institution; General Electric Company; Eastman Kodak Company; Cawthron Institute
  - Alexander Agassiz, 1904–1910; HaleGE_01_00_002_02; Smithsonian Institution; Agassiz, Alexander, 1835-1910; Hale, George Ellery, 1868-1938; 57 pages (Box 2, Folder 2)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 2, frames 646 to 703.
    Astronomy; Astronomy--Research; Physics; Astrophysics; Solar radiation; Hale, George Ellery, 1868-1938
  - Agriculture, Secretary of, 1916–1928; HaleGE_01_00_002_03; 19 pages (Box 2, Folder 3)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 2, frames 704 to 723.
  - R. G. Aitken, 1905–1935; HaleGE_01_00_002_04; 118 pages (Box 2, Folder 4)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 2, frames 724 to 841.
  - Lawrence Aller, 1931; HaleGE_01_00_002_05; 3 pages (Box 2, Folder 5)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 2, frames 842 to 845.
  - J. S. Ames, 1900–1917; HaleGE_01_00_002_06; 36 pages (Box 2, Folder 6)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 2, frames 846 to 882.
  - Loring B. Andrews, 1936; HaleGE_01_00_002_07; 14 pages (Box 2, Folder 7)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 2, frames 883 to 897.
  - J. A. Anderson, 1928–1935; HaleGE_01_00_003_01; 184 pages (Box 3, Folder 1)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 2, frames 898 to 1081.
  - James R. Angell, 1901–1924; HaleGE_01_00_003_02; 251 pages (Box 3, Folder 2)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 2, frames 1082 to 1331.
  - E. M. Antoniadi, 1924–1930; HaleGE_01_00_003_03; 7 pages (Box 3, Folder 3)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 2, frames 1332 to 1340.
  - Henry E. Armstrong, undated; HaleGE_01_00_003_04; 1 pages (Box 3, Folder 4)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 3, frames 20 to 22.
  - Trevor Arnett, 1904–1936; HaleGE_01_00_003_05; 176 pages (Box 3, Folder 5)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 3, frames 23 to 197.
  - Svante Arrhenius, 1904–1926; HaleGE_01_00_003_06; 20 pages (Box 3, Folder 6)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 3, frames 198 to 218.
  - Attwill, undated; HaleGE_01_00_003_07; 1 pages (Box 3, Folder 7)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 3, frames 219 to 220.
  - A. Auwers, 1912–1915; HaleGE_01_00_003_08; 8 pages (Box 3, Folder 8)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 3, frames 221 to 229.
  - Edward Ayer, 1899; HaleGE_01_00_003_09; 3 pages (Box 3, Folder 9)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 3, frames 230 to 233.
  - Allan H. Babcock, 1910; HaleGE_01_00_003_10; 2 pages (Box 3, Folder 10)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 3, frames 234 to 236.
  - Harold D. Babcock, 1925–1933; HaleGE_01_00_003_11; 22 pages (Box 3, Folder 11)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 3, frames 237 to 259.
  - O. Backlund, 1904; HaleGE_01_00_003_12; 6 pages (Box 3, Folder 12)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 3, frames 260 to 266.
  - Francis H. Bacon Company, 1918; HaleGE_01_00_003_13; 5 pages (Box 3, Folder 13)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 3, frames 267 to 272.
  - L. H. Baekelund, 1916–1936; HaleGE_01_00_003_14; 9 pages (Box 3, Folder 14)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 3, frames 273 to 282.
  - I. W. Bailey, 1917; HaleGE_01_00_003_15; 5 pages (Box 3, Folder 15)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 3, frames 283 to 288.
  - M. B. Baillaud, 1908–1920; HaleGE_01_00_003_16; 16 pages (Box 3, Folder 16)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 3, frames 289 to 305.
  - C. H. Collins Baker, 1932–1933; HaleGE_01_00_003_17; 17 pages (Box 3, Folder 17)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 3, frames 306 to 323.
  - William C. Baker, 1915–1916; HaleGE_01_00_003_18; 21 pages (Box 3, Folder 18)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 3, frames 324 to 345.
  - H. G. Van de Sande Bakhuyzen, 1915–1916; HaleGE_01_00_003_19; 42 pages (Box 3, Folder 19)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 3, frames 346 to 388.
  - George J. Baldwin, 1907–1908; HaleGE_01_00_003_20; 16 pages (Box 3, Folder 20)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 3, frames 389 to 405.
  - Sir Robert Ball, 1901–1914; HaleGE_01_00_003_21; 45 pages (Box 3, Folder 21)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 3, frames 406 to 451.
  - W. P. Bancroft, 1919–1920; HaleGE_01_00_003_22; 4 pages (Box 3, Folder 22)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 3, frames 452 to 456.
  - Llewellys F. Barker, 1902–1924; HaleGE_01_00_003_23; 9 pages (Box 3, Folder 23)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 3, frames 457 to 466.
  - E. E. Barnard, 1898–1924; HaleGE_01_00_003_24; 178 pages (Box 3, Folder 24)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 3, frames 467 to 645.
  - E. C. Barrett, 1911–1936; HaleGE_01_00_004_01; 241 pages (Box 4, Folder 1)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 3, frames 646 to 887.
  - S. B. Barrett, 1899–1935; HaleGE_01_00_004_02; 103 pages (Box 4, Folder 2)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 3, frames 888 to 992.
  - Albert L. Barrows, 1919–1934; HaleGE_01_00_004_03; 44 pages (Box 4, Folder 3)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 4, frames 20 to 64.
  - H. Bateman, 1916–1920; HaleGE_01_00_004_04; 19 pages (Box 4, Folder 4)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 4, frames 65 to 84.
  - L. A. Bauer, 1898–1926; HaleGE_01_00_004_05; 90 pages (Box 4, Folder 5)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 4, frames 85 to 175.
  - F. E. Baxandall, 1904–1924; HaleGE_01_00_004_06; 7 pages (Box 4, Folder 6)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 4, frames 176 to 183.
  - Belgian League of Honor, 1937; HaleGE_01_00_004_07; 2 pages (Box 4, Folder 7)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 4, frames 184 to 186.
  - Alexander Graham Bell, 1906; HaleGE_01_00_004_08; 7 pages (Box 4, Folder 8)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 4, frames 187 to 194.
  - Sir Hugh Bell, 1916; HaleGE_01_00_004_09; 4 pages (Box 4, Folder 9)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 4, frames 195 to 199.
  - Louis Bell, 1911; HaleGE_01_00_004_10; 4 pages (Box 4, Folder 10)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 4, frames 200 to 204.
  - Bell Telephone Laboratories, 1930; HaleGE_01_00_004_11; 1 pages (Box 4, Folder 11)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 4, frames 205 to 206.
  - A. Belopolsky, 1904–1933; HaleGE_01_00_004_12; 92 pages (Box 4, Folder 12)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 4, frames 207 to 298.
  - H. Y. Benedict, 1932; HaleGE_01_00_004_13; 7 pages (Box 4, Folder 13)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 4, frames 299 to 306.
  - Bickers and Company, 1911; HaleGE_01_00_004_14; 10 pages (Box 4, Folder 14)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 4, frames 307 to 317.
  - Albert S. Bickmore, 1903; HaleGE_01_00_004_15; 5 pages (Box 4, Folder 15)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 4, frames 318 to 323.
  - M. B. Bielski, 1937; HaleGE_01_00_004_16; 9 pages (Box 4, Folder 16)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 4, frames 324 to 333.
  - Frank H. Bigelow, 1902–1911; HaleGE_01_00_004_17; 3 pages (Box 4, Folder 17)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 4, frames 334 to 337.
  - M. G. Bigourdan, 1908–1927; HaleGE_01_00_004_18; 21 pages (Box 4, Folder 18)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 4, frames 338 to 359.
  - J. S. Billings, 1902–1909; HaleGE_01_00_004_19; 9 pages (Box 4, Folder 19)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 4, frames 360 to 369.
  - E. W. Birge, 1902–1919; HaleGE_01_00_004_20; 10 pages (Box 4, Folder 20)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 4, frames 370 to 380.
  - V. Bjerknes, 1924–1926; HaleGE_01_00_004_21; 25 pages (Box 4, Folder 21)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 4, frames 381 to 406.
  - Pietro Blaserna, 1909–1914; HaleGE_01_00_004_22; 7 pages (Box 4, Folder 22)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 4, frames 407 to 414.
  - E. W. Blatchford, 1899–1913; HaleGE_01_00_004_23; 18 pages (Box 4, Folder 23)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 4, frames 415 to 433.
  - Mildred Bliss, 1937; HaleGE_01_00_004_24; 2 pages (Box 4, Folder 24)
    This folder is represented in the microfilm edition of the Hale Papers by reel 4, frames 434 to 436.
  - Franz Boas, 1916; HaleGE_01_00_004_25; 2 pages (Box 4, Folder 25)